we've had a similar goal for quite some
time
it was compute the derivative other as
many functions as possible and we have
done a lot we figured out polynomials
and trigonometric terms we figured out
how to do things like the product we
figured out how to do things like a
composition we know how to do quotients
we know how to do sums we know an
enormous amount but there's one class
that we don't know yet and that's
Exponential's for example we do not know
how to take the derivative yet of X to
the power of sine of X so how can we
solve something like this what I want to
use what I'm going to exploit is a nice
little fact about logarithms and the
fact is this if I'm going to take the
natural log of a e to the power of B
then one of the rules of logarithms is
that this exponent that I have it can
come brought down at the front B times a
natural log of a now I want to suppose
you're taking the derivative of this
if exponents are hard things like X to
the sine X if those are hard well we do
know what the derivative of a product is
we've got the product rule for that
so because the natural log sort of
transforms exponents into products it's
going to be able to transform something
that's challenging into something as
effectively just a product rule so let's
see how this actually works in an
example I take my y equal to X the power
of sine of X and before I just try to
compute dy DX I'm going to go and take
the natural log of both sides first that
is I'm going to compute the natural log
of Y and the natural log of the X to the
power of sine of X and then our goal is
going to be if I have it written in this
form I'm gonna take the derivative of
both sides here now why have I helped
myself the key idea is this I've got the
X to the sine of X this is kind of like
an a to the B and I can apply my log
rule I can take this sine of X and I can
bring it down so what this is gonna have
on the right hand side is the derivative
of the sine of X times the natural log
of X what happened over here on the left
well this is a chain rule an outside
function the natural logarithm the
inside function y of X so what's its
derivative
it's the drew the upside which is one
over whatever the inside is one over Y
times the derivative the inside dy/dx
that's me apply my chain rule so apply
my chain rule over here I applied a log
rule over there I can take the
derivative of product another take the
derivative of sine times the natural log
of X I just use the product rule so what
do I have I'm going to leave the left
hand side sine goes to coast plus the
natural log plus sine times the dru the
natural log which is 1 over X so I've
applied my product rule here ok so I'm
happy with this but I want to do a
little bit more work let's get rid of
all this other nonsense what I want to
do is I don't want this Y here any
longer
I want my derivative to be some function
of X so I want to manipulate this but I
can both move the Y up to the other side
and I know that Y is X to the power of
sine of X so I can isolate it and take
this Y here move it over and what I get
is the derivative ektu X is there's the
Y exit sine of x times all of this other
stuff so that is my final answer for the
derivative with respect to X of this
function X to the sine of X and you can
see that it is kind of a long and messy
expression here but this is just how
this logarithmic differentiation works
it makes it possible for us to compute a
derivative that we didn't know how to do
before